In this lesson, we're going to do something very exciting.
And that very exciting thing is debugging.
Okay, maybe not.
Maybe debugging is not that exciting a part of programming.
Um, because it's trying to solve something that's not working.
But having said that, there is nothing more satisfying than fixing a problem in your code that is really
being annoying you, so you will get used to it.
And the two problems we're addressing both have to do with the ball.
Now, although technically speaking, this is actually a bug, it's just features we haven't implemented
completely.
But firstly, when we start our game, our ball doesn't start in the middle.
Instead it just starts sort of kind of where it left off.
And secondly, it just moves in whatever direction it was previously going.
So this quite literally makes it impossible when the game starts and our ball heads straight to the
ground.
So how do we solve this problem?
Well, don't look at me.
You're the programmer.
Use your programming skills and coding skills and problem solving skills to make the ball start in the
middle.
And also make the ball automatically start going up when the game starts.
Can you do that?
I'll be waiting.
Pause the video and give it a try.
So how did you go?
Well, let's see how you could have done this.
First things first.
To make sure our ball starts in the middle.
We can easily do this.
We just go to motion and bring in this.
Go to block.
Change it to zero x and let's say 60 y.
And then add it to the start of any of our scripts inside the ball sprite.
Now when we hit start you'll see that our ball starts in the center.
Great.
We're getting somewhere.
The next problem, however, is that sometimes our ball goes straight down, which isn't a train smash.
But for consistency's sake, let's make sure our ball starts with an upward motion.
And again, the fix for this isn't too complex.
It's all to do with what direction our ball is pointing.
So just like how we set the ball's position from the start, we can also set the direction it's pointing.
So dragging in this block, we can set the direction to zero degrees and then also bring it to the start
of our script.
Now, each time we click start, you'll notice that the game is consistent with the ball's position
and direction.
And with this, your game is very playable.
But hold on to your hats because in the next lesson, we will take this simple game to the next level
with level, difficulty, animations and more.